A Guide to the Moody Family Papers, 1750-1881
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Moody Family, Papers, 1750-1881
Library of Virginia
40535
0.45 cubic feet
Moody Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Serve photocopies.
Staff should consult item numbers when retrieving originals as folder and box numbers will not match the finding aid.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Vermillion, January 2004. Item 130 added by the donor in February 2012.
Biographical Information
The Moody family was a prominent planter family that resided in Brunswick, Greensville, and Southampton Counties and Petersburg, Virginia; and Mississippi, North Carolina, and Tennessee.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1750-1881, of the Moody family of Petersburg, and Brunswick and Greensville Counties, Virginia; and Mississippi, North Carolina, and Tennessee. Consists of certificates, correspondence, deeds, estate records, plats, receipts, report cards, and slave lists. Correspondence principally concerns southern plantation life during the period of western migration in the southern states, illness and death of family members, crop production, slaves, fashion, and religion. There are also transcripts of the correspondence, which patrons should consult for more information relevant to the letters.
Arrangement
Arranged into the following six series: I. Correspondence, 1829-1881; II. Financial and Bankruptcy Files, 1829-1872; III. Slave Files, 1817-1861; IV. Legal Files, 1806-1857; V. Deeds and Plats, 1750-1879; and VI. Alice Moody Report Cards, 1854-1855.
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1829-1881 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  Consists of letters mostly written to Martha William (Wright) Moody (1816-1885) of Brunswick County, Virginia, and North Carolina, from family members. The letters span much of her life beginning in 1829 when she goes to school and ending in 1881 about four years before her death. Notable correspondents include George W. Charlton (1797-1863), Charles Fenton Mercer Dancy (1814-1875), Martha Alice (Moody) Leigh (1838- 1906), John Mason Moody (1809-1877), John Mason Moody, Jr. (1840-1890), Julia Ann Patterson (1820-1866), Martha Robinson (Crump) Wright (1793-1871), Weldon Edwards Wright, William H. Wright (d. 1836).
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Letter. Martha Robinson Wright, Greensville County, Virginia, to Martha William Wright, Brunswick County, Virginia, 18 February 1829, 1; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter. William H. Wright, Lexington, Tennessee, to Martha William Wright, Northampton County, North Carolina, 28 April 1829, 2; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter. Reverend George W. Charlton, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Martha William Wright, Brunswick County, Virginia, 5 September 1829, 3; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter. William H. Wright, Henderson, Tennessee, to Martha William Wright, Northampton County, North Carolina, 15 December 1829, 4; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter. Martha Robinson Wright Charlton, Greensville County, Virginia, to Martha William Wright, Brunswick County, Virginia, 22 February 1830, 5; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter. Reverend George W. Charlton, Greensville County, Virginia, to Martha William Wright, Brunswick County, Virginia, 30 March 1830, 6; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter (typescript). Henry D. Mason, Franklin County, Tennessee, to John M. Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 22 May 1830, 7; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter. William H. Wright, Bolivar, Tennessee, to Martha William Wright, Northampton County, North Carolina, 18 December 1830, 8; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter. Reverend George W. Charlton, Greensville County, Virginia, to Martha William Wright, Norfolk, Virginia, 8 June 1831, 9; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. Unknown author, Jackson, Tennessee, to John Mason Moody, Raleigh, North Carolina, 7 December 1831, 10; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. William H. Wright, Bolivar, Tennessee, to Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 8 February 1833, 11; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. William H. Wright, Bolivar, Tennessee, to Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 26 April 1833, 12; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. John M. Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, to Richard Crump, 4 May 1833, 13; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Invitation. John Butts, Belfield, Greensville County, Virginia, to Martha William Moody, 23 July 1833, 14; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. William H. Wright, Bolivar, Tennessee, to John M. Moody, Northampton, North Carolina, 22 August 1833, 15; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. William H. Wright, Bolivar, Tennessee, to John M. Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 28 May 1834, 16; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. Francis W. Dancy, Athens, Alabama, to William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 17; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter (typescript). William H. Wright, Bolivar, Tennessee, to Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 29 October 1834, 18; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter. Julia Ann Patterson, Petersburg, Virginia, to Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 19 March 1935, 19; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. Charles Fenton Mercer Dancy, Decatur, Alabama, to Mary Mason Moody, North Carolina, 2 September 1835, 20; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. Mary Louise Page, Petersburg, Virginia, to Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 21 November 1836, 21; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. David M. Dancy, Decatur, Alabama, to William Moody, Raleigh, North Carolina, 7 December 1836, 22; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. William B. Williamson, Clinton, Mississippi, to John Mason Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 8 July 1837, 23; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. William B. Williamson, Clinton, Mississippi, to John Mason Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 3 March 1838, 24; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. Alice Wren Patterson, Petersburg, Virginia, to Martha William Moody, North Carolina, 29 May 1840, 25; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. John Mason Moody, Gaston, North Carolina, to Martha William Moody, North Carolina, 4 October 1840, 26; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter. Mary Louise Page, Petersburg, Virginia, to Martha William Wright, Greensville County, Virginia, 5 September ca. 1840, 27; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Invitation. Governor Dudley, Raleigh, North Carolina, to John M. Moody, 11 December 1841, 28; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. Weldon e. Wright to John M. Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, ca. June 1843, 29; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. Arthur Eldridge, Shelby, Tennessee, to Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 20 October 1844, 30; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notes. Made by John Mason Moody for a speech (?), ca. 1844, 31; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Invitation. Governor Morehead of North Carolina to John M. Moody, December 1844, 32; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. Francis Marion Wright, Halifax, North Carolina, to Martha William Moody, Northampton, North Carolina, 7 March 1845, 33; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. M. E. D. [Mary E. L. Drinkard?] to Martha William Moody, Columbus, Mississippi, 12 January 1846, 34; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. Julia Ann Patterson, Petersburg, Virginia, to Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 15 July 1846 (?), 35; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. Julia Ann Leigh, Boydton, Virginia, to Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, August 1846, 36; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter. John Mason Moody, Columbus, Mississippi, to Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 5 January 1847, 37; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. John M. Moody, Columbus, Mississippi, to Martha W. Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 18 January 1847, 38; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. Weldon Edwards Wright, Camden, Arkansas, to John Mason Moody, Columbus, Mississippi, 20 February 1849, 39; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. Martha Robinson Wright Charlton, Petersburg, Virginia, to Martha William Moody, Columbus, Mississippi, 17 December 1849, 40; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. Martha William Wright Charlton and Georgeanna Charlton, Petersburg, Virginia, to Martha William Moody, Columbus, Mississippi, November ca. 1850, 41; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. John M. Moody, Mobile, Alabama, to Martha W. Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 22 February 1853, 42; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. John H. Peele, Normal College, North Carolina, to John M. Moody, Weldon, North Carolina, 11 April 1857, 43; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. J. F. Simmons, Weldon, North Carolina, to child of John M. Moody, Columbus, Mississippi, 18 November 1857, 44; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. Mary Elizabeth Lockhart to Martha Leigh, 25 July 1861, 45; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. Mary Elizabeth Lockhart, Columbus, Mississippi, to Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 26 January 1862, 46; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. Mary Charlton, Petersburg, Virginia, to Martha William Moody, "Woodlawn," Garysburg, North Carolina, March 1862, 47; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. Dr. Hezekiah Gilbert Leigh, surgeon for the Confederate States of America at Hamilton Crossings in Spotsylvania County, Virginia, to Martha Leigh, Northampton County, North Carolina (?), 18 April 1863, 48; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. C. A. Durham to Martha William Moody, 10 January 1864, 49; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter. Thomas L. Lea, camp near Kinston, North Carolina, to Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 19 February 1865, 50; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. A. M. R. (?), Charleston, South Carolina, to Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 14 March 1866, 51; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. Mary Charlton, Petersburg, Virginia, to Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, 15 May 1868, 52; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. John Mason Moody, Jr., Lowndes County, Mississippi, to Martha Leigh, Petersburg, Virginia, 7 September 1868, 53; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. Martha William Moody, Lowndes County, Mississippi, to her daughters and her sister, 25 September 1868, 54-55; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. John Mason Moody, Jr., Lowndes County, Mississippi, to Martha Leigh, Petersburg, Virginia, 25 January 1870, 56; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. John Mason Moody, Jr., "Woodlawn," Garysburg, North Carolina, to Martha Alice Leigh, Petersburg, Virginia, ca. 1871-1872, 57; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. Mary Charlton to Martha William Moody, Garysburg, North Carolina, ca. 1872-1875, 58; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. C. H. Hall, Greenwood, Virginia, to Hezekiah Gilbert "Gib" Leigh, Petersburg, Virginia, 27 July 1872, 59; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. John Mason Moody, Jr., Columbus, Mississippi, to Martha Leigh, Petersburg, Virginia, 17 December 1872, 60; 2 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. "Annie", Ashland, Hanover County, Virginia, to Martha Leigh, 11 August 1873, 61; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. Martha William Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, to Martha Leigh, Petersburg, Virginia, 31 October 1875, 62; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. John Mason Moody, Northampton County, North Carolina, to Martha William Moody, June 1876, 63; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. Martha William Moody to H. A. Lockett, December 1877, 64; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. Virginia Gordon Moody, Lowndes County, Mississippi, to Martha William Moody, Petersburg, Virginia 1 May 1881, 65; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Financial and Bankruptcy Files, 1829-1872 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Comprises financial accounts and files including bankruptcy certificates, receipts, and a notice of public auction of the land of John M. Moody. There are also accounts and promissory notes for John M. Moody and William Moody that are unrelated to bankruptcy.
  Arranged chronologically. Item 130 appears in this series, out of item number order. It was interfiled after being added to the collection by the donor in 2012.
  - Statement of bonds due to William Moody, 23 April 1829, 66; 8 p.
  - Accounts. John M. Moody with unidentified merchants, 1832, 67; 1 leaf.
  - Promissory note. John M. Moody with Tamlin Avent, 25 October 1844, 68; 2 p.
  - Adjudication of bankruptcy. John M. Moody, 14 April 1868, 69; 3 p.
  - Voluntary bankruptcy petition. John M. Moody, 12 November 1869, 70; 3 p.
  - Bankruptcy receipt. John M. Moody, 18 March 1870, 71; 1 leaf.
  - Bankruptcy certificate. John M. Moody, 21 March 1870, 72; 2 p.
  - Notice for public auction of land. John M. Moody, 20 March 1872, 73; 2 p.
  - Receipt, Dr. H. G. Leigh, vacant lots A & B, Harrison Street, Petersburg, 30 April 1872, 130; 1 leaf
- Slave Files, 1817-1861 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  These files generally contain lists of slaves owned by John M. Moody. Some lists contain names and information concerning the age and sex, value, and food needed to feed the slaves.
  Arranged chronologically. Files with no date arranged alphabetically at end of series.
  - Deed for slaves. John M. Moody, 16 May 1817, 74; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - List of slaves and the quantity of corn it takes to feed them. John M. Moody, 30 January 1836, 75; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Statement of slaves belonging to John M. Moody, 4 January 1842, 76; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Number of slaves that has cloth for clothes and list of slaves for sale, 25 October 1843, 77; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - List of slaves on plantation in Mississippi. John M. Moody, 13 April 1850, 78; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - List of slaves. John M. Moody, 19-20 February 1857, 79; 4 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - List of slaves, 17 January 1858, 80; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - List of slaves and meat and meal to feed them, 1861, 81; 4 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - List of slaves. John M. Moody, n.d., 82; 3 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - List of field hands, n.d., 83; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - List of slaves, n.d., 84; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - List of slaves, n.d., 85; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - List of slaves, n.d., 86; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - List of slaves, n.d., 87; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - List of slaves and values, n.d., 88; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - List of slaves by sex, n.d., 89; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - List of small slaves and ages, n.d., 90; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Lot. No. 3," list of slaves with value, 91; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Negro draw," names of slaves and value, n.d., 92; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Legal Files, 1806-1857 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Consists of the legal files principally pertaining to the estate settlements of William Harris, William Moody and William Wright, for whom John M. Moody was executor. There is also a typescript of a will, written 3 April 1806 and proven June 1806, for Francis Darcy.
  - Typescript of Francis Dancy's will, 3 April 1806, 93; 2 leaves.
  - Estate inventory of William Wright, 3 December 1827, 94; 3 leaves.
  - Power of attorney. John P. Wyatt, 25 August 1832, 95; 7 leaves.
  - Estate inventory of William Moody, September 1839, 96; 2 leaves.
  - Estate accounts of William Moody, 24 October 1839, 97; 3 leaves.
  - Inventory of slaves in the estate of William Moody, 1841, 98; 3 leaves.
  - Receipt for debt paid on William Moody estate, 8 September 1847, 99; 2 leaves.
  - Receipt for purchase from William Harris estate, 30 November 1848, 100; 2 leaves.
  - Receipt for guardian's fees for Susan and James Harris paid by John M. Moody, 31 November 1848, 101; 2 leaves.
  - Dispute arbitration. John M. Moody and T. J. Jarratt and Company, 9 June 1856, 102; 13 leaves.
  - Receipt for lawsuit payment. John M. Moody, 9 October 1857, 103; 1 leaf.
- Deeds and Plats, 1750-1879 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
  Contains deeds and plats cheifly noting lands purchased in Greensville and Southampton Counties, Virginia, and Northampton County, North Carolina, by John M. Moody, William Moody and other members of the Moody family. Deeds and plats dated 1750-ca. 1815 primarily concern the related of Norwood and Pugh family. Within this series there are also documents related to the land transfers including promissory notes and receipts for payment for land tracts, title certificates, and articles of agreement.
  - Deed. William Norwood, 17 March 1749, 104; 3 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Deed. John Jones, 28 May 1754, 105; 4 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Deed. John Jones, 6 August 1756, 106; 4 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Land grant. William Hudson, 16 November 1790, 107; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Plat. Henry Hayley, 6 November 1797, 108; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Plat. Frederick Moody, 8 December 1804, 108a; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Deed. Eaton Pugh, 16 July 1806, 109; 3 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Plat. Francis Dancy estate, 25 November 1808, 109a; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Receipt for purchase of property. William Moody, 22 January 1816, 109b; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Deed. Robert Pare, 1 June 1816, 110; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Deed. Eaton Pugh, 24 December 1817, 111; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Receipt for purchase of two acres of land. William Moody, 5 February 1818, 112; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Deed. William Moody, 26 August 1818, 113; 4 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Deed. William Moody, 25 July 1818, 114; 3 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Deed. Nelson Hays, 13 May 1822, 115; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Certificate of relinquishment of title. William Monoghan, 25 January 1823, 116; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Articles of agreement. William Moody, 8 February 1825, 117; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Deed. Thomas Porch, 20 November 1826, 118; 3 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Plat. Mary A. Pugh, 28 April 1831, 119; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Plat. Nathaniel Tucker, 2 June 1831, 120; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Deed. Benjamin Crew, 16 August 1831, 121; 4 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Plat. Richard R. Moss, 15 April 1834, 122; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Deed. Bird Lundy, 11 February 1839, 123 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Promissory note for payment on land tract. John M. Moody, 4 September 1849, 124; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bond to title of land. John M. Moody, 24 November 1849, 125; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Deed. Virginia Charthin, 27 April 1872, 126; 2 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Deed. Martin Hill and Company, 9 May 1879, 127; 4 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Partial plat. Moody family, n.d., 128; 1 leaf. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Alice Moody Report Cards, 1854-1855 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Notes grades earned for Martha "Alice" Moody (1838-1906) in her educational studies at Petersburg Female College during the 1854-1855 term.